A Guide to the Papers of K. Edward Lay
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Dwellings-Albemarle County and Charlottesville
  - Rosneath, (Dabney Carr or Peter Carr), Albemarle, ca. 1827, 1845, 1910 1991 (Box 19)
  - Rougemont, (Dickinson Home; Peachylorum), Keswick, 1824, 1951 1990 (Box 19)
  - Round Hill, (Derwood S. Chase Home), Earlysville, 1940 n.d. (Box 19)
  - Round Top, (Dr. Benjamin Franklin Randolph Home; Mill Quarter; Sharon; Joseph Wilmer owner), Carters Bridge, 1834, 1945 1977-1993 (Box 19)
  - Royal Orchard, (Frederick W. Scott Home; Scotts Castle), Afton, 1913, 1917 1968-1996 (Box 19)
  - Rugby, (Andrew Farish Home; Rugby Hall; Major General Thomas Lafayette Rosser Home; Rosser Lane Boys School), Cottage Lane, Charlottesville, ca. 1850, 1880s 1974-1993 (Box 19)
  - Rutledge, (Farish House), near Earlysville, mid 19th century 1976-1999 (Box 19)
  - "R" General 1976-1993 (Box 19)
    Ramsbury House, Albemarle, 20th century; Raynham Hall, Keswick Hunt, ca. 1920, 1975; Red Fields, Charlottesville, 20th century; Red Gate Farm, Keswick, ca. 1832; Red Hill, Albemarle; Red Horse Farm, Albemarle, ca. 1840, 1930s, 1968-1969; Red House Antiques, (Cosby Robertson House), mid-late 19th century; Reed-Garrison House, Charlottesville, 1875; Charles Rich House, Blue Ridge Road, Charlottesville, ca. 1930; Ridge Street House, Charlottesville, 1925; Ridgefield, Albemarle; River Ridge, Free Union; Ridgeview Farm, Albemarle
    Roads End Farm, Scottsville; Roberts House, Hickory Ridge, Albemarle, mid 20th century; Jessie W. Robinson House, Charlottesville, 1896; S. Jeter Robinson House, Charlottesville, 1913; R. Merritte Robinson House, Charlottesville, 1911; Rock Hall, Albemarle, 18th century; The Rockery, Crozet, 20th century; Rocklands, Earlysville, 1840s; Rogers House, (Reed Home), Albemarle, late 18th century; 1910; Rogers House, (Giles Rogers House), Albemarle, late 1770s, 1900, 1910; Rogers Place, Stony Point, 18th century; Rose Hill Farm, (Smith House), Albemarle, ca. 1820-1840; Roseland, Albemarle, ca. 1800; Roslyn, Albemarle, ca. 1840; Ross House, (Michael Ross), Charlottesville, 1930; Rox, Ivy, 1814, ca. 1861; Royal Acres, Keswick; Royal Oaks, James River; Ruddington, Ivy, 19th century; Rugby Farm, Keswick Hunt, ca. 1820, 1950s; Rugby Apartments, University Circle, 1925-1926; Rugby Road Homes, Charlottesville, 1962; Ruston House, (Gleason Home); Rugby Road Homes, Charlottesville, 20th century
  - Sears Roebuck House, (J. J. Porter Home), Charlottesville, early 20th century 1990-1992 (Box 19)
  - Seven Gables Farm, (Ephraim Seamonds, Jr. Home; David Wood Farm), Albemarle, 1803 1976-1994 (Box 19)
  - Seven Maples, (David Mills Home; Mills House), Earlysville, late 18th century n.d. (Box 19)
  - Seven Oaks, (John Bolling Garrett Home; Clover Plains, Blacks Tavern), Yancey Mills, 1847-1847, 1906 1986-1990 (Box 19)
  - Shack Mountain, (Tusculum), Charlottesville, 1935-1936 1995 (Box 19)
  - Shadows, The (William D. Tilman Home; Tilman House), Albemarle, early 19th century, ca. 1872, 1940s 1976-1995 (Box 19)
  - Shadwell, (Peter Jefferson tract; Thomas Jefferson's birthplace; a Jefferson Farm), Shadwell, 1737, burned 1770 1991-1993 (Box 19)
  - Shelton House, Covesville, ca. 1860 1978-1994 (Box 19)
  - Sherwood, (Mary Eliza Carter Home), Carters Bridge, ante 1835, razed 1953, 1979 1989 (Box 19)
  - Shirland House, (James Nelson Moon Home; Shareland), Albemarle, ca. 1870 1987-1995 (Box 19)
  - Simms House, Free Union, ca. 1825 n.d. (Box 19)
  - Simpson-Wingfield-Vowles House, (Anderson Wingfield Home, 1835; John Timberlake/William B. Phillips, owners, 1837; John Vowles Home, 1841-1871; Episcopal Parsonage, 1871), Charlottesville, 1832-1835, razed late 1960s 1965-1996 (Box 19)
  - Smith Place, (John M. Smith Home; Mad Hatter Farm; Thomas Smith Home; William P. Smith Home), Albemarle, ca. 1794, ca. 1824, ca. 1867 1981 (Box 19)
  - Sneed House, (Stapleton C. Sneed Home), Charlottesville, ca. 1846 1991 (Box 19)
  - Solitude (Christopher Wingfield Home; Thomas Tourmans Land; Frank Wingfield Home), Albemarle, late 18th century, ca. 1890, ca. 1910, 1915, 1924, 1954 1958-1991 (Box 19)
  - Solitude Farm (William Alcock Home; Solitude; Home Tract; Gantt Home; Sutherland Farm), Crossroads, ca. 1810, ca. 1910 1980-1993 (Box 19)
  - Southall-Venable House, (Lee Park site), Charlottesville, early 19th century 1991-1998 (Box 19)
  - Sowell House, (Pleasant Sowell Home), Albemarle, early 19th century, ca. 1830, ca. 1840s, 1993 1977-1994 (Box 19)
  - Springdale Farm, (Winston House), near Simeon, Albemarle, 1845, ca. 1905, 1979-1980 1982-1996 (Box 19)
  - Spingfield & Tower, (Reuben Lindsay Home; Bolling W. Haxall; hexagonal stone tower ruins), Albemarle, early 19th century, 1897 1979-1992 (Box 19)
  - Spring Hill, (Charles Harper Home), Ivy, ca. 1810-1825, ca. 1830-1845, 20th century 1977 (Box 20)
  - Spring Hill Claim House, Spring Hill Farm, Ivy, 18th century n.d. (Box 20)
  - Spring Hill Farm, near Scottsville, 1842, ca. 1898 1977 (Box 20)
  - Spring Valley, (Charles Massie Home; John Brockenbrough Home), Albemarle, 18th century 1990-1991 (Box 20)
  - Stanford Hall, (Bacon Family House 1824, ca. 1875, 1939 1967 (Box 20)
  - Stevens-Peyton House, (C. B. Stevens Home; Thomas P. Peyton Home; Mitchell Van Yahres Home), 1892 1979 (Box 20)
  - Stevens Place, Sugar Hollow, 19th century 2000 (Box 20)
  - Stone Chamber, Pigeon Top Mountain 1987-1991 (Box 20)
  - Stone Gate, (Dr. John Morris Home; Woods Log House), Earlysville, early 19th century, 1962 1980 (Box 20)
  - Stone House, (Caperton Stone Bungalow), Ivy, early 20th century 1987-1990 (Box 20)
  - Stonefield, (Stonefield Carriage House; Bushnell-Wilkinson Carriage House, Mason Gordon, owner; Belle J. Bushnell, owner), Charlottesville, ca. 1880s or 1910, 1927, 1965 1981 (Box 20)
  - Stonemont, Albemarle, late 19th century, 1970s 1992 (Box 20)
  - Stony Point, (William Moon Home), near Scottsville, ca. 1800 n.d. (Box 20)
  - Strange House, (Colonel John Bowie Strange House; Albemarle Military Institute; Johnson Home for the Aged), Charlottesville, 1855 1995 (Box 20)
  - Strawberry Hill, (The Meadows; Colonel Reuben Lindsay Home; Captain James Lindsay Home; Patton Home), Lindsay, 1775, ca. 1801, early 19th century, 1911 burned 1991 (Box 20)
  - Strode, (Mrs. Albert Gildersleeve Home), Farmington, 20th century n.d. (Box 20)
  - Su Casa, (Prospect Hill; Harvey A. Basham Home; Dr. Charles W. Hurt Home), Charlottesville, 1929-1931 1975-1999 (Box 20)
  - Sumter House, (Thomas Sumter home site), 18th century, 1940s 1990 (Box 20)
  - Sun Hill, (J. Garland Home), ca.1850, 1880, 1960 1978 (Box 20)
  - Sunny Bank, (Andrew Hart Home; The South Garden), North Garden, ca. 1797 1974-1997 (Box 20)
  - Sunnyfields, (Sunnyside; Lucius P. Battle Home), Simeon, ca. 1835, late 19th century 1972-1997 (Box 20)
  - Sunnyside, (Blake Harris Home; Frederick Doveton Nichols Home; Colonel R. T. W. Duke Home; William Carroll's Place; Ira Garrett Home), Barracks Road, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, ca. 1800, 1857, 1863, 1918, 1958 1990-1996 (Box 20)
  - Sunnyside Farm Managers House, (built for R. T. W. Duke), Barracks Road, University of Virginia, ca. 1900, 1990 razed 1989-1995 (Box 20)
  - "S" General 1984-1997 (Box 20)
    The Saeter, Sugar Hollow, Albemarle, ca. 1866; Glebe of Saint Anne's Parish, Albemarle, moved 1950; St. Gabriel, Albemarle, ca. 1860; Sandridge, (Spring Gardens), Albemarle, early 20th century, 1990; Saunders-Wilson House, Charlottesville, ca. 1824; Schelford, (Truman Dodson House), Farmington Hunt, 20th century; Schildwachter House, Charlottesville, 1934; School Spring Farm, Buck Mountain, 1780, 1880s, 1966; Scottland Farm, Albemarle, ca. 1800; Scribner House, Charlottesville, 1925; Sempervirens, (Old Austin House), Buck Mountain, late 18th century
    Shackelford-Bannister House, Charlottesville, 1860; Shadows, Scottsville, ca. 1830; Shady Lawn, Farmington Hunt, early 19th century; The Shanty, Charlottesville, 18th century, razed 1938; Shelton Farm, Albemarle, 18th century, ca. 1830, early 20th century; Shifflett Log House, Browns Cove, relocated?; Shifflett House, Charlottesville, 1925; Shirk House, Albemarle, late 19th century; Shiloh Hill, (Phillips- Macreth House), Ivy, late 19th century, late 1920s; Short Hills, Albemarle County, 1948-1949; Sinclair House, Charlottesville, ca. 1880; Sirius, Farmington Hunt, 1982; Skyline Farm, Albemarle, 19th century; Sleepy Hollow, Albemarle, ca. 1955, 1988
    Smith House, Albemarle; Smith (George and Erlyne Smith), Albemarle, 1890; Smith House, (John A. Smith House), Charlottesville, 1905; Smith-Marshall House, Charlottesville, 1906; Snead-Pence House, Charlottesville, 1900; Social Hall, Howardsville, ca. 1820; Solitude, Albemarle, ca. 1800; Somerset Farm, Charlottesville, 20th century; Sparks-Garrett House, Charlottesville, 1899; Spaulding House, Charlottesville, 1920; John Spaulding House, Albemarle, 1908; Spring Hill Baptist Church, Advance Mills, 1883, 1919, 1954, 1976; Spring Hill Baptist Church, Albemarle, ca. 1910; Spring Hill Farm, Albemarle, 1850s, Springdale, Keswick, ca. 1910, 1980s razed, 1970s
    Stainback House (Colthurst Farm), 1962-1963; Steptoe House, Cismont, ca. 1890- 1891; William Stevens House (Randolph Major House), Bellair, ca. 1947; Stilwin (Sunnydale, Stilwyn), Albemarle, 18th century, razed, ca. 1915; Stinson House, Scottsville, 19th century; Stonefield, Stony Point, Stoneleigh, Red Hill, early 29th century; Strickland House, Crozet, 1905; Sunny Brae, Albemarle; Sutker Farm, Albemarle, 1890; Swan Lake, Free Union, 1995
  - Tall Oaks (Cedar Hill; Jerry Kirksey Home), Keswick, 1852, 1966 1978-1993 (Box 20)
  - Tallwood, (Tucker Coles Home; Upper Quarter), ca. 1803, ca. 1810, late 19th century, early 20th century 1980-1996 (Box 20)
  - Tarry, (Black owndership, Massie Tarry), Albemarle, ca. 1836 1980 (Box 20)
  - Temple Hill, (James Kinsolving House), late 18th century, Albemarle, 1956-1957, 1960 1976-1990 (Box 20)
  - Terrell House, (1st house in Charlottesville; Micajah Chiles Home; Farmers Bank; City Parking Garage site), ca. 1762, razed 1850 1982-1983 (Box 20)
  - Tiverton, (Dr. Frederick Owsley Baylor House; patterned after White House), Albemarle, 1896, 1925-1926, 1936-1938 1984-1995 (Box 21)
  - Totier Creek Farm, (Locust Shades), Albemarle, 1760, ca. 1860, 1990s 1978-1995 (Box 21)
  - Tower House, Charlottesville, 1850s, 1902, 1943 1974-1998 (Box 21)
  - Townley Saddlebag Log House n.d. (Box 21)
  - Tree Tops, Farmington, 1930-1931, 1976-1977 n.d. (Box 21)
  - Trinidad, Browns Cove, 18th century 1995-1999 (Box 21)
  - Tuckaway, Esmont, 1912 n.d. (Box 21)
  - Tuckedaway, Yancey Mills, 1775, ca. 1830, early 20th century 1977-1986 (Box 21)
  - Tudor Grove, (Bally-Les-Braden; boyhood home of Colonel John S. Mosby), Albemarle, ca. 1832, early 20th century 1994 (Box 21)
  - Tufton I, (Thomas Jefferson Randolph House), Albemarle, ca. 1815, ca. 1833-1845 1976 (Box 21)
  - Tufton II, (Thomas S. Macon House), Albemarle, ca. 1833-1845 1977 (Box 21)
  - Turkey Run, (hunting lodge), Albemarle, late 19th century n.d. (Box 21)
  - Twin Orchards, Free Union, late 19th century 1976 (Box 21)
  - Twin Springs, (John Foster Home), Albemarle, 1780, 1838 1986-1995 (Box 21)
  - "T" General n.d. (Box 21)
    Tall Pines, Albemarle, 20th century; Tally-Ho, Keswick; Tank Hut, Charlottesville, Tanbark, Howardsville, early 1900s; Tandem Farm, Ivy, ca. 1900, 1991; Tanglewood, Greenwood, 1900- 1917; Tank Hut, Charlottesville, ca. 1900-1917; Dr. Frank Taylor House, Albemarle, 1963, 1976; Temple Place, Charlottesville, ca. 1870; The Terrace, Scottsville; Thomas Place, Albemarle, ca. 1900; 1931 Thomson Road, Charlottesville; Three Chopt Acres, Albemarle; Thurman House, Charlottesville, ca. 1895; Thurston Properties, Crozet; Tilman House, Albemarle, 19th century; Timberlake House (Edmund Berkeley House), Albemarle, 1847; James E. Timberlake House, Charlottesville, 1886; Tisdale, Albemarle; Tompkins House, Scottsville, mid-19th century; Samuel Tompkins House, (Treetops), Albemarle, early 19th century; James Toms House, Earlysville, 1904; Benjamin Tonsler House, Charlottesville, 1875-1879; Trail's End (Trails End), Charlottesville, early 20th century; Travellers Rest, Albemarle, 1816; Tremain House, Albemarle, 1950; Trevillian-Tennyson House, Charlottesville, 1893; Trice-Towe House, Charlottesville, ca. 1850; Trimble House, Scottsville, 1900; Turner-LaRowe House, Charlottesville, 1892; Turner Mountain Road, Ivy; Twelve Oaks, near Scottsville, ca. 1830
  - Underhill House, Batesville, 1890 1993 (Box 21)
  - Upper Pantops, Albemarle, ca. 1928 n.d. (Box 21)
  - Upper Plantation, (William R. Wood House; Wentworth; Joseph G. Bullock Farm; Christopher Gilmer Home), Simeon, ca. 1740, ca. 1790, ca. 1810, ca. 1790, 1934, ca. 1961, ca. 1973 1988-1989 (Box 21)
  - "U" General 1978-1995 (Box 21)
    Unidentified houses; University Circle House, Charlottesville; Updike, Free Union, 1963; Updike House, Ridge Street, Charlottesville; Robert L. Updike House, Prospect Avenue, Charlottesville, 1904; Updike-Anthony House, Charlottesville, 1897
  - Valley Point Farm, Ivy, ca. 1825 1976 (Box 21)
  - Valmontis, (Carr House; Shackelford Home), Albemarle, late 18th century, ca. 1830 1995-1996 (Box 21)
  - Verdant Lawn, (Alexander Garrett Home; Old Simpson Place), Albemarle, ca. 1800 1963-1997 (Box 21)
  - Verulam, (Courtland Van Clief House), Sugar Hollow, Albemarle, 1941 1976-1998 (Box 21)
  - Via Log House, Sugar Hollow, Albemarle, ca. 1845, 1905, 1915 1975 (Box 21)
  - Viewmont, (Colonel Joshua Fry Home; Governor Edmund Randolph, owner; Captain John Harris Home; Lottie Moon birthplace, 1737, 1941 1939-1991 (Box 21)
  - Villa Crawford, (Robert B. Crawford House), Keswick, ca. 1912 1999 (Box 21)
  - Villino Lambeth, (Lambeth House; The Dell), University of Virginia, Charlottesville, 1912 1991-1995 (Box 21)
  - Vowles Townhouse 1, (John Vowles House), Charlottesville, 1823 1967-1993 (Box 21)
  - Vowles Townhouse 2, (John Vowles House), Charlottesville, ca. 1839 1993 (Box 21)
  - "V" General 1980-1995 (Box 21)
    Valentine House, E. High Street, Charlottesville, razed 1957; Valentine House, 7 1/2 Street, Charlottesville; Valentine-Nichols House, Charlottesville, 1924; Valley Cottage, Albemarle; Adam Via Place, Barboursville, 1830; Viewpoint Farm, Albemarle; Vowles Town Houses
  - Wakefield House, Appleberry Mountain, Albemarle, early 19th century, 1830s, ca. 1900 1989 (Box 21)
  - Wakefield, (Richard Durrett House), Earlysville, ca. 1781, 1938 1991-1997 (Box 21)
  - Wakefield Log Saddlebag House, (Richard Durrett, owner), ca. 1781 n.d. (Box 21)
  - Walker House, (William Walker House), Warren, ca. 1803, 1976 1976-1998 (Box 22)
  - Walnut Grove, (Marsh Walker Home; The Farm), mid 19th century, ca. 1872 1976-1982 (Box 22)
  - Walnut Hill (Nimrod Bramham House), Albemarle, early 19th century 1989 (Box 22)
  - Walnut Hill, (Garth Home), Scottsville, 1889 1988 (Box 22)
  - Walnut Lawn, White Hall, ca. 1790, 1940, 1969 1976-1990 (Box 22)
  - Walnut Level, (Olde Plantation; Ennisfree Village; Charles W. Antrim Home), Browns Cove, ca. 1810 1950-1990 (Box 22)
  - Walters House, (Ferguson Funeral Home), Charlottesville, 1900 1994-1995 (Box 22)
  - Walters-Brown House, Charlottesville, ca. 1875 1993 (Box 22)
  - Walters-Page House, (Nicholas Page Home), Batesville, ca. 1830 1974-1991 (Box 22)
  - Walters-Witkin House, Charlottesville, ca. 1881, ca.1910 n.d. (Box 22)
  - Watson House, (Judge Egbert R. Watson House), Charlottesville, 1861 1980 (Box 22)
  - Waver Tree Hall, (Quincy Adams Shaw Home; Colonel H. D. Newcomb Home), Batesville, 1859, ca. 1900, ca. 1921 1989-1998 (Box 22)
  - Wayland House, Crozet, ca. 1855, ca. 1880 1976-1994 (Box 22)
  - Wertland, (William Wertenbaker Home), Charlottesville, ca. 1830, 1983 1977-1997 (Box 22)
  - Westbury, Batesville, ca. 1830, ca. 1840, ca. 1870 1979-1993 (Box 22)
  - Westcote, (Summer Hill; Andrew Leslie Blair Home), Howardsville, 1830s 1978-2000 (Box 22)
  - Westerlea, Farmington Hunt, ca. 1851 n.d. (Box 22)
  - Westleigh, (Ivy Creek; Higginson School; William Wirt Gilmer Home; J. T. Woods Home; Kellam Home; John O. Higginson Home; J. D. Wilde Home), Ivy, 19th century 1976-1995 (Box 22)
  - Westover, Albemarle, 1915-1916 1991-1999 (Box 22)
  - Wheeler House, (Joshua Wheeler House; William Dudley Home), Albemarle, ca. 1845 1982-1993 (Box 22)
  - Whilton, (Lucy LeGrand Home), Greenwood, 1914, 1936, 1988 1988 (Box 22)
  - Whiskey Ridge, (Elisha Williams House), Free Union, 1830s 1984-1995 (Box 22)
  - Whitchris, (Blenheim Claim House), Albemarle, ca. 1730s 1977-1981 (Box 22)
  - White Cross, (Stephen Price Maury Home; Huntley Home), Charlottesville, 1891, 1900 1977 (Box 22)
  - White Gate, (Wood-Evans House), Crozet, ca. 1830, ca. 1850, ca. 1920 1981 (Box 22)
  - White Hall Farm, (Whitehall Farm; Sunny Hill; Indian Chief Martin King burial place), mid 19th century 1989-1990 (Box 22)
  - Wilhoit Farm, (Ezekiel Whilhoit, Jr. Farm), & Wilhoit Home Tract; (Milton Wilhoit Home; Wilhoit Mill Farm), Nortonsville, ca. 1825 1973 (Box 22)
  - Willoughby, (Captain Eugene Davis House; Colonel L. J. Owen Home; Benjamin Gentry Home; Duncan Philips, owner), Charlottesville, 1850, 1931 1980-1991 (Box 22)
  - Windie Knowe, (Hunting Lodge; William W. Minor Vineyard; traded for Glen Echo), Albemarle, ca. 1770, 1850 1978 (Box 22)
  - Windsor, (Windsor Hill; James Gavin Field Home), Cismont, ca. 1848 1979-1982 (Box 22)
  - Wingate, (Garth House), Owensville 1979-1983 (Box 22)
  - Wingfield House, (Robinson and James McLaurain Business; Dr. C. L. Wingfield Home), Warren, ca. 1789 1992 (Box 22)
  - Wingfield House, (Thomas Wingfield Home), Alberene, 18th century 1979 (Box 22)
  - Winter Haven, Keswick, ca. 1850 n.d. (Box 22)
  - Wits End, (Mrs. Mark Henderson Home), Charlottesville, ca. 1935 n.d. (Box 22)
  - Wood End Farm, Albemarle, ca. 1905 1985 (Box 22)
  - Wood House, (Yalden-Thompson Farm), Earlysville, ca. 1858 1990 (Box 22)
  - Woodburne, (Hill Horn; Daniel M. Railey Home), Proffit, ca. 1825 1979-1993 (Box 22)
  - Woodland, Albemarle, (John Dunkum Home; Remonds; Woodlawn; Colonel Redman Home), ca. 1820, 1929 1963-1993 (Box 23)
  - Woodlands, (Richard Wingfield Home; Honorable J. R. Wingfield birth place, Albemarle, 1842, 1890s n.d. (Box 23)
  - Woodlea, (Dr. John D. Smith House), Batesville, ca. 1890, 1945 burned 1991-1995 (Box 23)
  - Woodson House, Albemarle 1998-1999 (Box 23)
  - Woodville, (Richard H. Allen Home; William Woods Home), Albemarle, ca. 1800 1990-1992 (Box 23)
  - Woodville (Walter Coles Home; Old Woodville; Mavesyn), 1796, 1832, 1948 1973-1993 (Box 23)
  - Word-Wertenbaker House, (Thomas Jefferson Wertenbaker Home), Charlottesville, 1840s, 1985 1982-1985 (Box 23)
  - Wyndhurst, (Sally Ann McCoy House; Colonel Thomas L. Preston Home; Charity S. Pitts Boarding House; Preston Place Kitchen), Charlottesville, ca. 1815 1977 (Box 23)
  - "W" General 1976-1994 (Box 23)
    John Walker House; Walnut Springs, Albemarle; Isaac Walters House, Charlottesville, 1922, 1961; Walton Homestead, (Richmond Walton House), Albemarle, ca. 1761; Walton-Gentry House, Crozet, ca. 1910; Ward-Brown-Gay House, Charlottesville, 1889; Warren Old Cabin, Warren, 1930s; Watson, Meadowbrook Heights; Watson House, Second Street, Charlottesville, 1880-1881; Watson House, Wertland Avenue, Charlottesville, 1905; Watson-Beasley House, Charlottesville, ca. 1880; Watson-Bosserman House, Charlottesville, 1870; Watson-Carriage House, Charlottesville, 1981, 1911; Watson-McGrady House, Charlottesville, ca. 1889; Watson-Tomas House, Charlottesville, 1883-1888; Watson-Wood House, Charlottesville, ca. 1814
    Weiss House, Charlottesville, 1925; Wellons House, Charlottesville, 1938; Wells House, Albemarle, 1900; West Cairns, site of Kluge Rehabilitation Center, ca. 1912; West Main Street Houses, Charlottesville; West Wind, Farmington, 1939; Wheeler Farm, Albemarle, 1800; Wheeler House, E. High Street, Charlottesville, 19th century; Wheeler House, West Main Street, Charlottesville, 1893; Wheeler-Alderman House, Charlottesville, 1881-1886; Wheeler-Coulter House, Charlottesville, 1893; Wheeler-Keller House, (Ridge Oak Apartments), 1881-1886, 1951; Whistlefield Farm, Greenwood, 1954; White Gate Farm, Crozet, ca. 1885, 1930s; The White House, Hilltop Road, Charlottesville, 20th century; John S. White House, Charlottesville, 1903; White Oak Cottage, (Old Seamonds Place), Buck Mountain, 1812; White Oaks, Albemarle; White Pine, Albemarle
    Wildwood, Garth Road, ca. 1918; Wilkerson House, Ruckersville, ca. 1812, 1901; Wilkins-English House, Charlottesville, 1889; Williams House, Earlysville, 19th century; Williams House, (Dr. John W. Williams House), Crossroads, 1887-1890; Willow Bank, Howardsville, 1850s; Willow Cottage House, Charlottesville, ca. 1855-1857, ca. 1871-1875; Willow Oak, Earlysville, early 20th century; Wilton Tract, Charlottesville, ca. 1900; Windermere, Farmington, 20th century; Windfield, Albemarle, ca. 1896; Windmill Hill, Keswick; Windsor Circle, Farmington; Windsor Hill, late 19th century; Windy Hill, Crozet, 1913; Wine Street House, ca. 1884; Wingfield Home, Esmont, ca. 1814
    Wolftrap Farm, Esmont, 19th century, 1935; Ira Wood House, Earlysville, early 19th century, 1880s; R. H. Wood House, Charlottesville, ca. 1892; Wood-Bidgood House, Charlottesville, 1891, ca. 1910; Woodard House, University Manor, Charlottesville, 1904; Woodard House, 9th Street, Charlottesville, 1930; Woodbine, Farmington Country Club, 20th century; Woodbound, Keswick, 1925, 1982; Woodbourne, Buck Island, 19th century; Woodfield, Keswick; Woodland Farm, Albemarle, ca. 1900; Woodridge, Garth Road, Farmington Country Club, ca. 1967; Wyndybrow, Farmington
  - "Y" General 1995 (Box 23)
    Yeargain House, (John Yeargain House; Yeargain's Liquor Store; Law Office of Justice William Robertson), Charlottesville, ca. 1800, ca. 1866, 1967; York House, Charlottesville, 1946; Young House, (Dr. Young Home), Albemarle, late 18th century
- Dwellings-Other Counties
  - The Barn, Augusta County; Berry Hill, Petersburg, ca. 1800; Big Cobler Farm, Fauquier County; Boxwood Farm, Hot Springs, late 18th century; Broad Lawn, Hot Springs, Bath County, ca. 1890; Buckland Farm, Prince William County, ca. 1743; Cartersville Tavern, Cartersville, Cumberland County, ca. 1810; Clare-mont, Caroline County, ca. 1845; Clifton Plantation, Cumberland County, 1732; Colraine, Gloucester County, late 19th century; Covenant Farm, Wytheville, ca. 1900; Creswell Farm, Bedford County; Dunlap Farm, Augusta County, ca. 1880; Evergreen Plantation, Accomack County, ca. 1766 1981-1989 (Box 23)
    Farley, Culpeper County, ca. 1792; Foolish Pleasure, Prince Edward County, ca. 1820-1840; Greenbrier Farm, Greenbrier County, West Virginia, ca. 1820; Greenway Plantation, Charles City County, 18th century; Greenwood Farm, Augusta County, ca. 1750; Hidden Valley Farm, Shenandoah County, ca. 1790; Hickory Hill, Rockbridge County, ca. 1824; James River Farm, Appomattox County, Malvern Hall, Hot Springs, Bath County, 1905; Merrifield, Shenandoah Valley, 1793; Merryhill, Stanleytown, Henry County, 20th century; Montpelier, Orange County, 1750s, 1797-1800; Mount Sion, Caroline County, ca. 1722
    North Cliff, Culpeper County, ca. 1848; Pine Knoll Farm, Augusta County, 1843; Pinifer Park, Chesterfield County; Poplar Forest, Bedford County, 1812; Poplar Grove, Nottoway County, 1801-1803